Out of Kenilworth Oral History Project OHP022
People's Archive, MLK Library
Out of Kenilworth Oral History Project
2003-2005
People's Archive, MLK Library
Lapp, Jospeh
OHP022
13 Linear feet
8 Boxes
Arrangement
Series 1: Transcripts Scope and Contents Materials in this series include transcripts, including digital copies, for all interviews. Series also includes audio and PowerPoint copies of a presentation given at the 2006 Kenilworth History celebration and Northeast DC Historical Society, and a sermon by Elmer Lapp. Series 2: Interviews Scope and Contents Materials in this series include master of the oral histories on audio cassette. There are duplicate copies of all audio recordings. There are no taps for 22-009, 22-010, 22-011, 22-057, 22-058, 22-059, 22-076, 22-077, 22-090, and 22-091.
Biographical / Historical
Joseph E. Lapp was born in the Kenilworth neighborhood of Washington, D.C., where his parents established a church/mission on Douglas Street NE called "Fellowship Haven." Lapp grew up in a white Amish-Menonite missionary family in the historically black neighborhood. He graduated from Calvin College with a degree in English. In 2003 began work on a community history and family memoir project. The project consisted of a series of oral history interviews and the publication of "Kenilworth: A DC Neighborhood by the Anacostia River" in 2006.
Custodial History
Joseph Lapp conducted these interviews between 2003 and 2005. The transcripts, audio recordings and digital files were donated to the Library in 2006.
Scope and Contents
Between 2003 and 2005 Joseph Lapp conducted a series of oral history interviews to document the history of Kenilworth, a historically black neighborhood. Interviewees included Lapp family members and the Fellowship Haven Church community. Topics include family stories, tenant's rights, the Kenilworth Park and Aquatic Gardens, and the Eastland Gardens community. Digital files include copies of all transcripts, a PowerPoint presentation given at Kenilworth History Day celebration, and a general video of the Kenilworth History Day celebration. Additional materials include audio recordings of the Kenilworth History celebration and Northeast Historical Society presentations, and a recording of a sermon by Elmer Lapp entitled "Witnesses in Samaria."
Oral History; African Americans; Neighborhoods; Kenilworth (Washington, D.C.); Religion
- Series 1: Transcripts
  Scope and Contents
  Materials in this series include transcripts, including digital copies, for all interviews. Series also includes audio and PowerPoint copies of presentation given at the 2006 Kenilworth History celebration and Northeast DC Historical Society, and a sermon by Elmer Lapp.
  - Lapp Family, 2003 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jean Ann (Miller) Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Wesley Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Rosanna (Rose) and Marvin Kauffman, 2003 August 19 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Oren Yoder, 2003 August 21-2003 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Joanna Hochstetler Yoder, 2003 August 21-2003 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oren and Joanna Yoder, 2003 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eunice Lapp-Hill, 2003 October 12-2003 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Naomi Wilson, 2003 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Gladys Roy, 2004 January 12 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jeanne Wilson Woods, 2004 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 January 26-2004 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 January 26-2004 February 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Tim Lapp, 2004 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sandy Lapp, 2004 January 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lydia Lapp Martin, 2004 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Arthur Beiler, 2004 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lois Lapp, 2004 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Joyce Stoltzfoos Bley, 2004 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Troyer Gertrude, 2004 February 10-2004 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Frank Matthews, 2004 February 10 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Owen Davis, 2004 February 12 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Lewis Tice, 2004 April 21 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Harold Dean Miller, 2004 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ruth Shaw Watts, 2004 June 21 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Walter McDowney, 2004 August 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Wil Stephenson, 2004 August 3 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Denise, 2004 August 4 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Lillian Wright, 2004 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Sharon Williamson, 2004 August 29 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Clarice "Berta" Brown Ulu, 2004 November 3 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Tom Brown, 2004 November 12 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Lenora Dubard-Burke, 2004 November 12 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 November 28 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2004 November 28-2004 November 29 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Tyrone Miller, 2004 December 28 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pat Roy, 2004 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Stuart Butler, 2005 April 5 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Lashawn "Lisa" Moore Reynolds, 2005 May 28 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Cynthia Sharpe, 2005 November 12-2005 November 17 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2006 November 25-2006 November 29 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Series 2: Interviews
  Materials in this series include master of the oral histories on audio cassette. There are duplicate copies of all audio recordings. There are no taps for 22-009, 22-010, 22-011, 22-057, 22-058, 22-059, 22-076, 22-077, 22-090, and 22-091.
  - Electronic Copies of Transcripts (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Kenilworth Then and Now powerpoint presentation, 2006 February 18 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Kenilworth History Celebration, 2006 February 18 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Lapp Family, 2003 May 14 (Box 3, Folder 22-A)
  - Jean Ann (Miller) Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 14 (Box 3, Folder 22-001)
  - Wesley Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 22-002)
  - Wesley Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 22-003)
  - Wesley Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 22-004)
  - Wesley Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 13 (Box 3, Folder 22-005)
  - Jean Ann (Miller) Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 14 (Box 3, Folder 22-006)
  - Jean Ann (Miller) Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 14 (Box 3, Folder 22-007)
  - Jean Ann (Miller) Schrock, 2003 August 12-2003 August 14 (Box 3, Folder 22-008)
  - Oren Yoder, 2003 August 21-2003 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 22-012)
  - Oren Yoder, 2003 August 21-2003 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 22-013)
  - Joanna Hochstetler Yoder, 2003 August 21-2003 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 22-014)
  - Joanna Hochstetler Yoder, 2003 August 21-2003 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 22-015)
  - Joanna Hochstetler Yoder, 2003 August 21-2003 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 22-016)
  - Oren Yoder, 2003 August 21-2003 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 22-017)
  - Oren and Joanna Yoder, 2003 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 22-018)
  - Oren and Joanna Yoder, 2003 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 22-019)
  - Eunice Lapp-Hill, 2003 October 12-2003 October 13 (Box 3, Folder 22-020)
  - Eunice Lapp-Hill, 2003 October 12-2003 October 13 (Box 4, Folder 22-021)
  - Eunice Lapp-Hill, 2003 October 12-2003 October 13 (Box 4, Folder 22-022)
  - Naomi Wilson, 2003 November 20 (Box 4, Folder Unknown)
  - Gladys Roy, 2004 January 12 (Box 4, Folder 22-025)
  - Gladys Roy, 2004 January 12 (Box 4, Folder 22-026)
  - Jeanne Wilson Woods, 2004 January 23 (Box 4, Folder 22-027)
  - Jeanne Wilson Woods, 2004 January 23 (Box 4, Folder 22-028)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 January 26-2004 February 2 (Box 4, Folder 22-029)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 January 26-2004 February 1 (Box 4, Folder 22-030)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 January 26-2004 February 2 (Box 4, Folder 22-031)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 January 26-2004 February 1 (Box 4, Folder 22-032)
  - Tim Lapp, 2004 January 27 (Box 4, Folder 22-033)
  - Tim Lapp, 2004 January 27 (Box 4, Folder 22-034)
  - Sandy Lapp, 2004 January 27 (Box 4, Folder 22-035)
  - Lydia Lapp Martin, 2004 January 29 (Box 4, Folder 22-036)
  - Lydia Lapp Martin, 2004 January 29 (Box 4, Folder 22-037)
  - Arthur Beiler, 2004 January 31 (Box 4, Folder 22-038)
  - Arthur Beiler, 2004 January 31 (Box 4, Folder 22-039)
  - Lois Lapp, 2004 January 31 (Box 4, Folder 22-040)
  - Lois Lapp, 2004 January 31 (Box 5, Folder 22-041)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 January 26-2004 February 2 (Box 5, Folder 22-042)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 January 26-2004 February 2 (Box 5, Folder 22-043)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2004 November 28-2004 November 29 (Box 5, Folder 22-044)
  - Joyce Stoltzfoos Bley, 2004 February 2 (Box 5, Folder 22-045)
  - Joyce Stoltzfoos Bley, 2004 February 2 (Box 5, Folder 22-046)
  - Troyer Gertrude, 2004 February 10-2004 February 19 (Box 5, Folder 22-047)
  - Troyer Gertrude, 2004 February 10-2004 February 19 (Box 5, Folder 22-048)
  - Frank Matthews, 2004 February 10 (Box 5, Folder 22-049)
  - Frank Matthews, 2004 February 10 (Box 5, Folder 22-050)
  - Owen Davis, 2004 February 12 (Box 5, Folder 22-051)
  - Owen Davis, 2004 February 12 (Box 5, Folder 22-052)
  - Owen Davis, 2004 February 12 (Box 5, Folder 22-053)
  - Gertrude Troyer, 2004 February 19 (Box 5, Folder 22-054)
  - Gertrude Troyer, 2004 February 19 (Box 5, Folder 22-055)
  - Lewis Tice, 2004 April 21 (Box 5, Folder 22-056)
  - Ruth Shaw Watts, 2004 June 21 (Box 5, Folder 22-060)
  - Ruth Shaw Watts, 2004 June 21 (Box 5, Folder 22-061)
  - Walter McDowney, 2004 August 1 (Box 6, Folder 22-062)
  - Walter McDowney, 2004 August 1 (Box 6, Folder 22-063)
  - Wil Stephenson, 2004 August 3 (Box 6, Folder 22-064)
  - Wil Stephenson, 2004 August 3 (Box 6, Folder 22-065)
  - Denise, 2004 August 4 (Box 6, Folder Unknown)
  - Lillian Wright, 2004 August 6 (Box 6, Folder 22-067)
  - Lillian Wright, 2004 August 6 (Box 6, Folder 22-068)
  - Sharon Williamson, 2004 August 29 (Box 6, Folder 22-069)
  - Sharon Williamson, 2004 August 29 (Box 6, Folder 22-070)
  - Sharon Williamson, 2004 August 29 (Box 6, Folder 22-071)
  - Clarice "Berta" Brown Ulu, 2004 November 3 (Box 6, Folder 22-072)
  - Clarice "Berta" Brown Ulu, 2004 November 3 (Box 6, Folder 22-073)
  - Tom Brown, 2004 November 12 (Box 6, Folder 22-074)
  - Tom Brown, 2004 November 12 (Box 6, Folder 22-075)
  - Lenora Dubard-Burke, 2004 November 12 (Box 6, Folder Unknown)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 November 28 (Box 6, Folder 22-078)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 November 28 (Box 6, Folder 22-079)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2004 November 28 (Box 6, Folder 22-080)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2004 November 28-2004 November 29 (Box 6, Folder 22-081)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2004 November 28-2004 November 29 (Box 6, Folder 22-082)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2004 November 28-2004 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 22-083)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2004 November 28-2004 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 22-084)
  - Tyrone Miller, 2004 December 28 (Box 7, Folder 22-085)
  - Tyrone Miller, 2004 December 28 (Box 7, Folder 22-086)
  - Pat Roy, 2004 December 31 (Box 7, Folder 22-087)
  - Pat Roy, 2004 December 31 (Box 7, Folder 22-088)
  - Stuart Butler, 2005 April 5 (Box 7, Folder 22-089)
  - Lashawn "Lisa" Moore Reynolds, 2005 May 28 (Box 7, Folder Unknown)
  - Cynthia Sharpe, 2005 November 12-2005 November 17 (Box 7, Folder 22-092)
  - Cynthia Sharpe, 2005 November 12-2005 November 17 (Box 7, Folder 22-093)
  - Cynthia Sharpe, 2005 November 12-2005 November 17 (Box 7, Folder 22-094)
  - Cynthia Sharpe, 2005 November 12-2005 November 17 (Box 7, Folder 22-095)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2006 November 25-2006 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 22-096)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2006 November 25-2006 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 22-097)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 22-098)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 22-099)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 22-100)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 22-101)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 7, Folder 22-102)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-103)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2006 November 25-2006 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-104)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2006 November 25-2006 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-105)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2006 November 25-2006 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-106)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-107)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-108)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-109)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2006 November 25-2006 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-110)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2006 November 25-2006 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-111)
  - Fannie Lapp, 2006 November 25-2006 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-112)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-113)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-114)
  - Elmer Lapp, 2005 November 25-2005 November 29 (Box 8, Folder 22-115)
  - Joe Lapp, 2006 February 21 (Box 8, Folder 22-116)
  - Joe Lapp, 2005 April 3 (Box 8, Folder 22-117)
  - Elmer Lapp (Box 8, Folder 22-118)
  - Kenilworth History Celebration, 2006 February 18 (Box 8, Folder 22-119)
  - Kenilworth History Celebration, 2006 February 18 (Box 8, Folder 22-120)